<?xml version="1.0"?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>George M. Durner (ORCID: 0000-0002-3370-1191)</origin>
        <pubdate>20200127</pubdate>
        <title>Catalogue of Polar Bear (Ursus maritimus) Maternal Den Locations in the Beaufort and Chukchi Seas and Nearby Areas, 1910–2018</title>
        <geoform>tabular digital data</geoform>
        <serinfo>
          <sername>Catalogue of Polar Bear (Ursus maritimus) maternal den locations in the Beaufort and Chukchi seas and nearby areas, 1910-2018</sername>
          <issue>ver. 2.0</issue>
        </serinfo>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace>Anchorage, AK</pubplace>
          <publish>U.S. Geological Survey, Alaska Science Center</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <othercit>Durner, G. M., 2010, Catalogue of Polar Bear (Ursus maritimus) maternal den locations in the Beaufort and Chukchi seas and nearby areas, 1910-2018 (ver. 2.0, January, 2020): U.S. Geological Survey data release, https://doi.org/10.5066/P9RPHH50.</othercit>
        <onlink>https://doi.org/10.5066/P9RPHH50</onlink>
        <lworkcit>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>U.S. Geological Survey, Alaska Science Center</origin>
            <pubdate>1984</pubdate>
            <title>Understanding and Forecasting the Response of Polar Bear Populations to a Rapidly Diminishing Sea Ice Environment</title>
            <geoform>website</geoform>
            <serinfo>
              <sername>Alaska Science Portal</sername>
              <issue>16</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
              <pubplace>Anchorage, AK</pubplace>
              <publish>U.S. Geological Survey, Alaska Science Center</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <othercit>This is a link to the broader USGS Alaska Science Center research project supported by these data. Users will find a description of the research project and links to associated reports, publications, and data products.</othercit>
            <onlink>https://alaska.usgs.gov/portal/project.php?project_id=16</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </lworkcit>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>This data reports on the approximate locations and methods of discovery of 530 polar bear (Ursus maritimus) maternal dens observed in the Beaufort and Chukchi seas and neighboring areas between 1910 and 2018, and archived partly by the U.S. Geological Survey, Alaska Science Center, and partly by the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service, Marine Mammals Management, in Anchorage, Alaska. Data fields include a unique and permanent USGS identifier for each record, the year when the adult would have been expected to depart the den with young, an index of whether the maternal den was confirmed or probable, coordinates of the den, substrate that each den occurred on, the agency source of each record, method of discovery of each den, method used to determine the position of each den, and estimated position uncertainty. Data were collected through standardized VHF aircraft surveys and satellite radio telemetry, field research activities in polar bear habitat, and anecdotal reports from other government agencies, coastal residents, and industry personnel. The polar bear maternal den records presented here supersede an earlier version of these data (Durner and others, 2010)</abstract>
      <purpose>The data were collected on maternal denning by polar bears that use the Beaufort and Chukchi seas. The data have been used to explain polar bear maternal denning including the distribution and timing of maternal denning, the choice of denning substrates (i.e., land versus sea ice), reproductive success, changes in maternal den distribution relative to sea ice change, and (in the case of terrestrial dens) map the land forms selected by bears for maternal denning. In general, the data have been used to explain polar bear ecology and to inform management agencies (e.g., the US Fish and Wildlife Service), however, these data are available for unrestricted use by the public. The polar bear maternal den records presented here supersede an earlier version of these data (Durner and others, 2010)</purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>1910</begdate>
          <enddate>2018</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>ground condition</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>As needed</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <descgeog>Beaufort Sea and Chukchi Sea of northern Alaska, Canada, and Russia</descgeog>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>162.8392</westbc>
        <eastbc>-22.849</eastbc>
        <northbc>83.52100</northbc>
        <southbc>63.36670</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt>
        <themekey>biota</themekey>
        <themekey>environment</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>NASA GCMD Earth Science Thesaurus</themekt>
        <themekey>Earth Science</themekey>
        <themekey>Biological classification</themekey>
        <themekey>Animals/vertebrates</themekey>
        <themekey>Mammals</themekey>
        <themekey>Carnivores</themekey>
        <themekey>Bears</themekey>
        <themekey>Species Life History</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>USGS CSA Biocomplexity Thesaurus</themekt>
        <themekey>Wildlife</themekey>
        <themekey>Mammals</themekey>
        <themekey>Marine mammals</themekey>
        <themekey>Threatened species</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>USGS Thesaurus</themekt>
        <themekey>Animals</themekey>
        <themekey>Vertebrates</themekey>
        <themekey>Mammals</themekey>
        <themekey>Science programs</themekey>
        <themekey>Animal behavior</themekey>
        <themekey>Bears</themekey>
        <themekey>Biogeography</themekey>
        <themekey>Animal tracking</themekey>
        <themekey>Telemetry</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>USGS Geographic Names Information System</placekt>
        <placekey>State of Alaska</placekey>
        <placekey>Chukchi Sea</placekey>
        <placekey>Beaufort Sea</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <taxonomy>
      <keywtax>
        <taxonkt>None</taxonkt>
        <taxonkey>Animals</taxonkey>
        <taxonkey>Mammals</taxonkey>
        <taxonkey>Vertebrates</taxonkey>
        <taxonkey>Bears</taxonkey>
        <taxonkey>Polar bears</taxonkey>
      </keywtax>
      <taxonsys>
        <classsys>
          <classcit>
            <citeinfo>
              <origin>Integrated Taxonomic Information System</origin>
              <pubdate>Unknown</pubdate>
              <title>Integrated Taxonomic Information System</title>
              <geoform>database</geoform>
              <serinfo>
                <sername>ITIS</sername>
                <issue>TSN 176604</issue>
              </serinfo>
              <pubinfo>
                <pubplace>online</pubplace>
                <publish>ITIS-North America</publish>
              </pubinfo>
              <othercit>Details of polar bear taxonomy were retrieved May 31, 2019, from the Integrated Taxonomic Information System online database: http://www.itis.gov</othercit>
              <onlink>http://www.itis.gov</onlink>
            </citeinfo>
          </classcit>
        </classsys>
        <taxonpro>Species identification was made by skilled observed in the field based on general appearance. Polar bears are not easily confused with other species.</taxonpro>
      </taxonsys>
      <taxongen>polar bears</taxongen>
      <taxoncl>
        <taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
        <taxonrv>Animalia</taxonrv>
        <taxoncl>
          <taxonrn>Subkingdom</taxonrn>
          <taxonrv>Bilateria</taxonrv>
          <taxoncl>
            <taxonrn>Infrakingdom</taxonrn>
            <taxonrv>Deuterostomia</taxonrv>
            <taxoncl>
              <taxonrn>Phylum</taxonrn>
              <taxonrv>Chordata</taxonrv>
              <taxoncl>
                <taxonrn>Subphylum</taxonrn>
                <taxonrv>Vertebrata</taxonrv>
                <taxoncl>
                  <taxonrn>Infraphylum</taxonrn>
                  <taxonrv>Gnathostomata</taxonrv>
                  <taxoncl>
                    <taxonrn>Superclass</taxonrn>
                    <taxonrv>Tetrapoda</taxonrv>
                    <taxoncl>
                      <taxonrn>Class</taxonrn>
                      <taxonrv>Mammalia</taxonrv>
                      <taxoncl>
                        <taxonrn>Subclass</taxonrn>
                        <taxonrv>Theria</taxonrv>
                        <taxoncl>
                          <taxonrn>Infraclass</taxonrn>
                          <taxonrv>Eutheria</taxonrv>
                          <taxoncl>
                            <taxonrn>Order</taxonrn>
                            <taxonrv>Carnivora</taxonrv>
                            <taxoncl>
                              <taxonrn>Suborder</taxonrn>
                              <taxonrv>Caniformia</taxonrv>
                              <taxoncl>
                                <taxonrn>Family</taxonrn>
                                <taxonrv>Ursidae</taxonrv>
                                <taxoncl>
                                  <taxonrn>Genus</taxonrn>
                                  <taxonrv>Ursus</taxonrv>
                                  <taxoncl>
                                    <taxonrn>Species</taxonrn>
                                    <taxonrv>Ursus maritimus</taxonrv>
                                    <common>Polar Bear</common>
                                    <common>TSN 180542</common>
                                  </taxoncl>
                                </taxoncl>
                              </taxoncl>
                            </taxoncl>
                          </taxoncl>
                        </taxoncl>
                      </taxoncl>
                    </taxoncl>
                  </taxoncl>
                </taxoncl>
              </taxoncl>
            </taxoncl>
          </taxoncl>
        </taxoncl>
      </taxoncl>
    </taxonomy>
    <accconst>None</accconst>
    <useconst>It is requested that the authors and the USGS, Alaska Science Center, be cited for any subsequent publications that reference this dataset.</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Alaska Science Center</cntorg>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>4210 University Drive</address>
          <city>Anchorage</city>
          <state>Alaska</state>
          <postal>99508</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>907-786-7000</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>ascweb@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <datacred>The authors recognize the contributions of Gerald W. Garner (USGS, deceased) who deployed satellite collars on female polar bears in the Chukchi Sea between 1987 and 1994. We acknowledge Stanislav E. Belikov (All-Russian Research Institute for Nature Conservation and Reserves) and Mikial S. Stishov (Wrangel Island State Nature Reserve), whose collaboration with Gerald W. Garner made possible the deployment of satellite collars on polar bears along Russia’s Chukotka Peninsula and Wrangel Island.  We wish to express our appreciation to numerous local residents and industry personnel whose observations added to the data in this report. Primary funding for this work to the USGS, Alaska Science Center, was provided by the USGS Climate and Land Use Change Research and Development Program and the USGS Changing Arctic Ecosystems Program. Additional support was provided by the USFWS, the U.S. Bureau of Land Management, the U.S. Bureau of Ocean Energy Management, BP Exploration – Alaska, ConocoPhillips – Alaska, ExxonMobil, Caelus Energy Alaska, Hilcorp Alaska, LLC, Eni Petroleum Co. Inc., Polar Bears International, the World Wildlife Fund, the University of Wyoming (National Science Foundation grant OPP 0732713), and prior to 1973, the State of Alaska. Funding for the USFWS, Marine Mammals Management, was provided by the State of Alaska, U.S. Bureau of Land Management, the U.S. Bureau of Ocean Energy Management, the National Fish and Wildlife Foundation, and the USGS.</datacred>
    <crossref>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>George M. Durner, Steven C. Amstrup, Todd C. Atwood, David C. Douglas, Anthony S. Fischbach, Jay W. Olson, Karyn D. Rode, and Ryan R. Wilson</origin>
        <pubdate>202001</pubdate>
        <title>Catalogue of Polar Bear (Ursus maritimus) Maternal Den Locations in the Beaufort and Chukchi Seas and Nearby Areas, 1910–2018</title>
        <geoform>tabular digital data</geoform>
        <serinfo>
          <sername>Data Series</sername>
          <issue>1121</issue>
        </serinfo>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace>Online</pubplace>
          <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <othercit>Durner, G.M., Amstrup, S.C., Atwood, T.C., Douglas, D.C., Fischbach, A.S., Olson, J.W., Rode, K.D., and Wilson, R.R., 2019, Catalogue of polar bear (Ursus maritimus) maternal den locations in the Beaufort and Chukchi Seas and nearby areas, 1910–2018: U.S. Geological Survey Data Series 1121 12 p. including appendixes, https://doi.org/10.3133/ds1121. [Supersedes USGS Data Series 568.]</othercit>
        <onlink>https://doi.org/10.3133/ds1121</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </crossref>
    <crossref>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Steven C. Amstrup and Craig L. Gardner</origin>
        <pubdate>199401</pubdate>
        <title>Polar bear maternity denning in the Beaufort Sea</title>
        <geoform>journal article</geoform>
        <serinfo>
          <sername>Journal of Wildlife Management</sername>
          <issue>58(1)</issue>
        </serinfo>
        <othercit>The Journal of Wildlife Management, Vol. 58, No. 1 (Jan., 1994), pp. 1-10 </othercit>
        <onlink>https://doi.org/10.2307/3809542 </onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </crossref>
    <crossref>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Jay W Olson, Karyn D. Rode, Dennis L. Eggett, T.S. Smith, R. R. Wilson, George M. Durner, Anthony S. Fischbach, Todd C. Atwood, and David C. Douglas</origin>
        <pubdate>201702</pubdate>
        <title>Collar temperature sensor data reveal long-term patterns in southern Beaufort Sea polar bear den distribution on pack ice and land</title>
        <geoform>journal article</geoform>
        <serinfo>
          <sername>Marine Ecology Progress Series</sername>
          <issue>564</issue>
        </serinfo>
        <othercit>Olson JW, Rode KD, Eggett D, Smith TS and others (2017) Collar temperature sensor data reveal long-term patterns in southern Beaufort Sea polar bear den distribution on pack ice and land. Mar Ecol Prog Ser 564:211-224. https://doi.org/10.3354/meps12000 </othercit>
        <onlink>https://doi.org/10.3354/meps12000</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </crossref>
    <crossref>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Karyn D. Rode, Jay Olson, Dennis L. Eggett, David C. Douglas, George M. Durner, Todd C. Atwood, Eric V. Regehr, Ryan R. Wilson, Tom Smith, and Michelle St. Martin</origin>
        <pubdate>201802</pubdate>
        <title>Den phenology and reproductive success of polar bears in a changing climate</title>
        <geoform>journal article</geoform>
        <serinfo>
          <sername>Journal of Mammalogy</sername>
          <issue>99(1)</issue>
        </serinfo>
        <othercit>Karyn D Rode, Jay Olson, Dennis Eggett, David C Douglas, George M Durner, Todd C Atwood, Eric V Regehr, Ryan R Wilson, Tom Smith, Michelle St. Martin, Den phenology and reproductive success of polar bears in a changing climate, Journal of Mammalogy, Volume 99, Issue 1, 1 February 2018, Pages 16–26, https://doi.org/10.1093/jmammal/gyx181</othercit>
        <onlink>https://doi.org/10.1093/jmammal/gyx181 </onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </crossref>
    <crossref>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>George M. Durner, Anthony S. Fischbach, Steven C. Amstrup, and David C. Douglas</origin>
        <pubdate>2010</pubdate>
        <title>Catalogue of Polar Bear (Ursus maritimus) Maternal Den Locations in the Beaufort Sea and Neighboring Regions, Alaska, 1910–2010</title>
        <geoform>tabular digital data</geoform>
        <serinfo>
          <sername>Data Series</sername>
          <issue>568</issue>
        </serinfo>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace>Reston, VA</pubplace>
          <publish>United States Geological Survey</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <othercit>Durner, G.M., Fischbach, A.S., Amstrup, S.C., and Douglas, D.C., 2010, Catalogue of polar bear (Ursus maritimus) maternal den locations in the Beaufort Sea and neighboring regions, Alaska, 1910–2010: U.S. Geological Survey Data Series 568, 14 p.</othercit>
        <onlink>https://doi.org/10.3133/ds568 </onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </crossref>
    <crossref>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Anthony S. Fischbach, Steven C. Amstrup, and David C. Douglas </origin>
        <pubdate>200706</pubdate>
        <title>Landward and eastward shift of Alaskan polar bear denning associated with recent sea ice changes</title>
        <geoform>journal article</geoform>
        <serinfo>
          <sername>Polar Biology</sername>
          <issue>30(11)</issue>
        </serinfo>
        <othercit>Fischbach, A.S., Amstrup, S.C. &amp; Douglas, D.C. Polar Biol (2007) 30: 1395. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00300-007-0300-4</othercit>
        <onlink>https://doi.org/10.1007/s00300-007-0300-4 </onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </crossref>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>Polar bear den records were derived from on-ground observations by residents and visitors in coastal northern Alaska, chance encounters by petroleum industry personnel, State, Federal and industry ground and aerial surveys for maternal dens in likely polar bear denning habitat, chance encounters during State or Federal polar bear field studies, and through standardized very-high frequency (VHF) aircraft radio-telemetry or satellite radio-telemetry of radio-equipped adult female polar bears.  Den records were classified as confirmed following compelling evidence that the structure was used for parturition (e.g., den tenure duration, subsequent observation of the adult with dependent young, post-denning site visitation showing evidence of denning).   Dens were classified as probable if there was compelling evidence that denning did occur (e.g., radio-collar sensors indicated prolonged high collar temperature relative to ambient temperatures and low activity relative to that of free-ranging bears) but lacked subsequent field observations of the den itself or the adult with dependent young.  Den site position was determined from communication with observers, review of topographic maps, aircraft navigation systems, or hand-held GPS receivers during on-ground site visits, from which coordinates were transcribed onto paper data sheets and then entered manually into an electronic database.  Den coordinates derived from satellite radio-telemetry were obtained electronically from the service provider (i.e., through Collecte Localisation Satellites, or CLS, Toulouse, France; http://www.argos-system.org/, or by Iridium satellite communications, Iridium Satellite Communications, McLean, VA, USA) and usually transferred electronically into databases.</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>No unexpected values exist in the data; all values are considered within expected range.</logic>
    <complete>Data set is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details. Users are cautioned that observations of maternal dens are dependent on the method of data collection; thus, certain methods may provide a better representation of den distribution than others.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>The position of dens discovered prior to 1999 and estimated from topographical maps (1:63,000) or aircraft navigation systems including reported dens, those discovered during aircraft VHF missions, and those discovered by USGS field crews conducting polar bear captures were recorded to the nearest minute of latitude and longitude. A horizontal uncertainty of ± 926 m (i.e., half of one minute of latitude) was assumed for these records. Following 1998, all conventional, FLIR, and VHF radio-tracking aircraft missions utilized onboard GPS to record den positions. Most satellite-linked tags used after 2003 had onboard GPS receivers. All den positions estimated with GPS were recorded to at least 1/10,000th of a degree and assumed to have a spatial error of ≤ 30 m. Positions estimated through the Argos system were reported to 1/1000th of a degree and had a spatial uncertainty ranging from 0.4 km to 7.6 km, depending on Argos message quality. Sea ice den locations are reported from a single field observation or a single satellite-linked position and, because sea ice continually drifts, do not reflect the location of the den during the entire winter. The position of land and fast ice (i.e., sea ice attached to land) dens determined by satellite-linked data are from the record(s) with the best location quality during den tenure, with ties of highest quality locations averaged for a final position. Follow-up visits to dens (i.e., on-ground visits) superseded the previous aircraft-derived or satellite telemetry-derived location.</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <method>
        <methtype>Field</methtype>
        <methdesc>Conventional – Encountered during other USGS polar bear field research efforts</methdesc>
      </method>
      <method>
        <methtype>Field</methtype>
        <methdesc>FLIR – Encountered with Forward-looking Infrared</methdesc>
      </method>
      <method>
        <methtype>Field</methtype>
        <methdesc>Report – Reported to USGS from other individuals or agencies</methdesc>
      </method>
      <method>
        <methtype>Field</methtype>
        <methdesc>Satellite – Encountered through satellite telemetry</methdesc>
      </method>
      <method>
        <methtype>Field</methtype>
        <methdesc>VHF_RADIO – encountered through very high frequency (VHF) telemetry</methdesc>
      </method>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Development of the data set by the USGS.  The data set is a compilation of observations from multiple sources.</procdesc>
        <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>The data and documentation have been revised as version 2.0. The title of the data has been revised. The data has been modified with the following fields added: Confirmation, Substrate, Position_method, Horizontal_error_m. Additional den site records covering years 2011-2018 have been appended. Seven den site records have been removed. Some positions have been modified due to recalculation. Metadata has been modified to modernize and improve documentation. Please see the version history file for a detailed description of changes from 1.0. Note: version 1.0 of this data can be accessed via the USGS Data Series 568, Catalogue of Polar Bear (Ursus maritimus) Maternal Den Locations in the Beaufort Sea and Neighboring Regions, Alaska, 1910–2010, Durner and others, 2010. https://doi.org/10.3133/ds568</procdesc>
        <procdate>2019</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <direct>Point</direct>
  </spdoinfo>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <geograph>
        <latres>0.0001</latres>
        <longres>0.0001</longres>
        <geogunit>Decimal degrees</geogunit>
      </geograph>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>World Geodetic System of 1984</horizdn>
        <ellips>World Geodetic System of 1984</ellips>
        <semiaxis>6378137</semiaxis>
        <denflat>298.257223563</denflat>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
  <eainfo>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>USGS_polar_bear_maternal_dens_1910-2018.csv</enttypl>
        <enttypd>Table containing polar bear maternal den location data in the Beaufort and Chukchi seas and neighboring areas, 1910-2018. Presented in a Comma Separated Value (CSV) formatted table.</enttypd>
        <enttypds>Author defined</enttypds>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Record</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Row number of the table</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Author defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>1</rdommin>
            <rdommax>530</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>DenID</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>USGS-assigned permanent identification number for each den</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Author defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>126</rdommin>
            <rdommax>1148</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Spring_year</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The year that neonate polar bears would have emerged from the den had the den been successful in producing cubs</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Author defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>1910</rdommin>
            <rdommax>2018</rdommax>
            <attrunit>year</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Data_source</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The agency that provided the den record</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Author defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>USGS</edomv>
            <edomvd>Den observation made by the US Geological Survey</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Author defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>USFWS</edomv>
            <edomvd>Den observation made by the US Fish and Wildlife Service</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Author defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>INDUSTRY</edomv>
            <edomvd>Den observation made by petroleum industry personnel</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Author defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>ADFG</edomv>
            <edomvd>Den observation made by Alaska Department of Fish and Game</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Author defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>LOCAL</edomv>
            <edomvd>Den observation made by residents or visitors to Arctic coastal regions</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Author defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>USFWS-ADFG</edomv>
            <edomvd>Dens discovered through a collaboration between the U.S. Fish &amp; Wildlife Service-Marine Mammals Management and the Alaska Department of Fish and Game</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Author defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Discovery_method</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Method used to discover the den</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Author defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>CONVENTIONAL</edomv>
            <edomvd>Dens discovered opportunistically during polar bear field research</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Author defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>FLIR</edomv>
            <edomvd>Dens discovered during Forward-looking Infrared surveys</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Author defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>REPORT</edomv>
            <edomvd>Dens discovered by other agencies or individuals and reported to the USGS</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Author defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>SATELLITE</edomv>
            <edomvd>Dens discovered by satellite-linked radio-telemetry</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Author defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>VHF_RADIO</edomv>
            <edomvd>Dens discovered by VHF radio-telemetry</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Author defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Latitude</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Latitude of the den position</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Author defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>63.3667</rdommin>
            <rdommax>83.5210</rdommax>
            <attrunit>decimal degrees</attrunit>
            <attrmres>0.0001</attrmres>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Longitude</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Longitude of the den position</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Author defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-179.9150</rdommin>
            <rdommax>179.8600</rdommax>
            <attrunit>decimal degrees</attrunit>
            <attrmres>0.0001</attrmres>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Confirmation</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>An indicator of confidence that the observation was a polar bear maternal den</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Author defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>C</edomv>
            <edomvd>Den verified by on-site visits by personnel and/or subsequent observations of the adult with dependent young</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Author defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>P</edomv>
            <edomvd>Dens with supporting information to indicate maternal denning (e.g., temperature, activity and signal quality of satellite telemetry data), but lacked a site visit or a subsequent observation of the adult with young</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Author defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Substrate</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Substrate that the den occurred on</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Author defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>L</edomv>
            <edomvd>Den was on land</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Author defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>F</edomv>
            <edomvd>Den was on fast ice (immobile sea ice frozen to land)</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Author defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>P</edomv>
            <edomvd>Den was on pack ice</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Author defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>U</edomv>
            <edomvd>Unknown if den was on land, land fast ice, or pack ice</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Author defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Position_method</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The method used to determine the position of the den</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Author defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>aircraft</edomv>
            <edomvd>Position estimated with aircraft navigation systems (non-gps)</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Author defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Argos LC=0</edomv>
            <edomvd>Position estimated by Argos LC class 0</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Author defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Argos LC=1</edomv>
            <edomvd>Position estimated by Argos LC class 1</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Author defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Argos LC=2</edomv>
            <edomvd>Position estimated by Argos LC class 2</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Author defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Argoc LC=3</edomv>
            <edomvd>Position estimated by Argos LC class 3</edomvd>
            <edomvds>AUthor defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Argos LC=A</edomv>
            <edomvd>Position estimated by Argos LC class A</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Author defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Argos LC=B</edomv>
            <edomvd>Position estimated by Argos LC class B</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Author defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Argos LC=Z</edomv>
            <edomvd>Position estimated by Argos LC class Z</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Author defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>field gps</edomv>
            <edomvd>Position estimated by gps on site (field, including aircraft)</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Author defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>map</edomv>
            <edomvd>Position assumed to have been estimated with a topographic map</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Author defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>satellite gps</edomv>
            <edomvd>Position estimated by gps-equipped satellite-radio tag attached to the polar bear</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Author defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Horizontal_error_m</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>An estimate of den position error</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Author defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>30</rdommin>
            <rdommax>7600</rdommax>
            <attrunit>meter</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Alaska Science Center</cntorg>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>4210 University Drive</address>
          <city>Anchorage</city>
          <state>Alaska</state>
          <postal>99508</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>907-786-7000</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>ascweb@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <resdesc>USGS Alaska Science Repository is the authoritative source for this data. Original version of the data can be accessed by request of the author.</resdesc>
    <distliab>Unless otherwise stated, all data, metadata and related materials are considered to satisfy the quality standards relative to the purpose for which the data were collected. Although these data and associated metadata have been reviewed for accuracy and completeness and approved for release by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>Zip</formname>
          <formvern>19.0</formvern>
          <formspec>7-Zip used to create zip file</formspec>
          <formcont>Zip file containing the data in CSV file format and FGDC metadata in XML and HTML formats.</formcont>
          <filedec>Any zip tool should be able to extract files.</filedec>
          <transize>0.3</transize>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>https://doi.org/10.5066/P9RPHH50</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <fees>None</fees>
    </stdorder>
  </distinfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Amy Benson</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Science Analytics and Synthesis</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>Mail Stop 306,</address>
          <address>= West 6th Ave. and Kipling St. DFC, Bldg. 810</address>
          <city>Lakewood</city>
          <state>CO</state>
          <postal>80225-0046</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>303-202-4087</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>albenson@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <resdesc>Ocean Biogeographic Information System USA (OBIS-USA). An alternate source for the data, also provides geospatial visualization.</resdesc>
    <distliab>Unless otherwise stated, all data, metadata and related materials are considered to satisfy the quality standards relative to the purpose for which the data were collected. Although these data and associated metadata have been reviewed for accuracy and completeness and approved for release by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>ZIP</formname>
          <formcont>Zip file containing the data in DwC-A file format and metadata in FGDC and EML XML formats.</formcont>
          <filedec>No compression applied</filedec>
          <transize>0.1</transize>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>https://www1.usgs.gov/obis-usa/ipt/</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <fees>None</fees>
      <ordering>See OBIS-USA website for download instructions.</ordering>
    </stdorder>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20200124</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Alaska Science Center</cntorg>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>4210 University Drive</address>
          <city>Anchorage</city>
          <state>Alaska</state>
          <postal>99508</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>907-786-7000</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>ascweb@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>